http://youtu.be/-RLDOq-sW6g
Tung Dinh _ VGU http://youtu.be/-RLDOq-sW6g
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So here's our stepper motor robot.
Đây là robot dùng motor bước
And let's review the components.
Ta sẽ lược qua về các thành phần
Up here is the launch pad.
Trên đây là launch pad
And we have two stepper motors, each one tied to a wheel.
Và 2 motors bước, mỗi cái đi với 1 bánh xe
There's one stepper motor tied to the left wheel,
1 cái ở đây, bánh trái
and another one to the right wheel.
và cái còn lại ở bên phải
We have two sensors.
Ta có 2 cảm biến ở đây
We have the left bumper sensor here, which is just a switch
cảm biến trái, là 1 công tắc
and the right bumper switch as well.
cái bên phải cũng vậy
On the protoboard here are the L293 motor drivers.
Trên breadboard ta có L293, là motor drivers
Here's the one driver, and over here is the second driver.
1 cái ở đây, cái thứ 2 ở kia
This pretty black chip here is the regulator,
Cái chip đen này là regulator
which takes power from the battery, the 8.4 volts,
lấy điện từ pin, 8.4V
and generates 5 volts out to power the launch pad.
chuyển sang 5V để chạy launchpad
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: The two sensors are connected to port E pins 1 and 0,
2 cảm biến được nối với port E pin 1 và 0
and the two stepper motors are connected to port B.
2 motors bước được nối với port B
And what are those back sensors, Jon?
Còn cái cảm biến sau là gì, Jon?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh.
oh
Well, every robot has to protect itself, and you
Mỗi robot đều phải tự bảo vệ hết
don't want to run into things going backwards,
và ta không muốn nó chạm cái gì ở sau
so the back ones are for future development.
cái đó để phát triển sau
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: All right.
Đúng rồi
So let's try it out.
Vậy ta test luôn
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right, here's the on switch.
Ok, đây là công tắc nguồn
Look out.
Nhìn đây
Stand back.
Lùi ra sau
It might explode.
Nó có thể nổ
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And this an approaching from the side
Ta bắt đầu ở phía bên này
where it turns in response.
khi nó bắt đầu phản ứng
Now, if you want to try the other configuration, where
Bây giờ, nếu bạn muốn thử ở chế độ khác
this is going to approach from the other angle,
khi nó chạm ở hướng khác
it should turn according to that finite state machine design.
nó sẽ quay dựa vào thiết kế máy trạng thái hữu hạ
Now, it's going to be harder for us to simulate, or envision the situation
Bây giờ, trường hợp này hơi khó biểu diễn
where both bumpers hit at the same time.
là khi cả hai công tắc chạm tường một lúc
It's unlikely, so because this one struck first,
bở 1 cái chạm trước
it's going to turn to the right.
nên nó sẽ quay phải trước
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
Đúng rồi
Will this robot protect itself, or will it fall off the table?
Con robot tự bảo vệ nó được chứ? hay nó sẽ rơi xuống bàn?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: It will fall off the table.
Nó sẽ rơi thôi